בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is ל"ז, lamed zayin, 37.
We pick up at the very top of ל"ז. lamed zayin. To
remind you where we are, the משנה mishna had the debate of
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and the חכמים chachamim about whether you can,
about what a knot of the לולב lulav has to be made
of. According to רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, only from the ארבעה מינים.
arba'a minim. בן מינו, bin mino, actually an interesting question if you
could use a part of the אתרוג etrog tree.
But anyway, that's what רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says because, and the
חכמים chachamim disagree, and רבא Rava explains the reasoning of רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda is not an aesthetic point, but it's actually a point
of the idea that לולב lulav requires a knot, so to use
anything else would be considered to be extraneous and adding to the
number of מינים. minim. I just mentioned in passing an interesting thought
about whether you could use part of the אתרוג etrog tree, because
is that also seen as extraneous since the אגד eged really consists
of three מינים, minim, not four. Something interesting to think about. Anyway,
רבא Rava says that once that's the point and it's not an
aesthetic point, you can even use parts of the tree of the
לולב lulav tree that are not aesthetic, like a piece of the
bark even if you could make a strip of bark, that could
be used then to knot the לולב. lulav. And now he's trying
to demonstrate this idea that even a part of the tree itself
is considered like a part of the ארבעה מינים, arba'a minim, even
if it's not the actual לולב, lulav, the actual הדס, hadas, the
actual ערבה, arava, even those, even the parts would be considered part
of the ארבעה מינים. arba'a minim. And he's going to demonstrate that
from a fascinating debate that's so fascinating that we didn't hear about
it about סוכה, Sukkah, you know, we didn't really hear about it
when we were doing the first two פרקים. perakim. And that is
a debate about whether you need to make the סוכה Sukkah out
of the ארבעה מינים. arba'a minim. So let's actually maybe pick up
with that at the bottom of ל"ו עמוד ב'. lamed vav amud
bet. And it says the following about if we did this yesterday,
but we'll do it again quickly today, about eight lines from the
bottom. ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, and רבא Rava says, מנא אמינא לה,
m'na amina la, the line starts with the word מיני. mini. מנא
אמינא לה דכתיב דעיקרא דדיקלא מיניה דלולבא הוא. M'na amina la de'chtiv
de'ikra de'dikla minei d'lulvahu.
Where do I know that this sort of vine on attached to
the palm tree, the actual bark itself or the trunk itself is
considered like part of the same מין min of the לולב. lulav.
Obviously, botanically it is, but how do I know הלכתית halachically it's
considered like part of the ארבעה מינים? arba'a minim? דתניא, D'tanya, we
taught in a ברייתא, braita, בסוכות תשבו, Basukkot teshvu,
you shall dwell in סוכות. sukkot. סוכה של כל דבר, Sukkah she'kol
davar, דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rebbi Meir. You can make it out
of anything, you know, the סכך, sechach, etc., as long as it
follows the criteria of not מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah and growing from
the ground. רבי יהודה אומר אין סוכה נוהגת אלא בארבעה מינים שבלולב.
Rebbi Yehuda omer, ein sukkah noheget ela b'arba minim she'balulav.
You can only make it out of the same ארבעה מינים arba'a
minim that you use for the לולב. lulav. That's what you have
to make the סכך sechach out of. ודין נותן, V'din noten, and
it's logic and it's logical that this should be the way. ודין
נותן V'din noten often introduces
a קל וחומר. kal vechomer. ומה לולב שאינו נוהג בלילות כבימים אינו
נוהג אלא בארבעה מינים, סוכה שנוהגת בלילות כבימים אינו דין שלא תהא
אלא בארבעה מינים. U'mah lulav she'eino noheg baleilot k'vayamim eino noheg ela
b'arba minim, sukkah she'noheget baleilot k'vayamim, eino din she'lo tehe ela b'arba
minim. A pretty bizarre קל וחומר. kal vechomer. You know, you can
then say almost anything you want should be demanded by a סוכה.
sukkah. And anyway, but okay, there's already a predisposition and we'll see
actually פסוקים p'sukim in עזרא Ezra that might push you in this
direction to sort of and to link these two things, so you
should also require the ארבעה מינים. arba'a minim. אמרו לו, Amru lo,
the rabbis said back to רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, interesting אמרו amru
since he was debating with רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, but anyway they,
because obviously this was a very דעת יחיד, da'at yachid, said to
him, כל דבר שאתה דנהו תחילתו להחמיר וסופו להקל אינו דין. kol
davar she'attah datcha techillato le'hachmir vesofo le'hakel eino din. Any קל וחומר
kal vechomer you make that starts off saying oh we should be
more מחמיר machmir by סוכה, sukkah, but in the end it's not
a חומרא, chumra, it's a קולא. kula. It's not a good קל
וחומר. kal vechomer. Why is it a קולא? kula? Top of ל"ז
עמוד א'. lamed zayin amud aleph. לא מצא ארבעה מינים ישב ויבטל?
Lo matzah arba minim, yaishiv u'batel?
Let's say you're making all these high demands, let's say you can't
satisfy those demands. You can't find enough ארבעה מינים arba'a minim to
make סכך sechach for your סוכה. sukkah. So what, should you not
sit in a סוכה? sukkah? According to you, you'll say well okay,
you don't have a סוכה sukkah you have to eat out of
the סוכה. sukkah. והתורה אמרה בסוכות תשבו שבעת ימים v'ha'Torah amra "Basukkot
teshvu shivat yamim," סוכה של כל דבר. sukkah she'kol davar. The Torah
says you should dwell in סוכות sukkot for seven days. סוכה Sukkah
out of anything. Which is fascinating, which basically makes the point that
every חומרא chumra we always oh just be מחמיר. machmir. Every חומרא
chumra almost always has a קולא kula associated with it. You're excluding
people, you're making it harder, you know, often has a קולא kula
associated with it that you're not being concerned, you know, sometimes you're
compromising בין אדם לחבירו bein adam l'chavero issues, but often also you're
being מיקל meikel in the sense of, you know, you're being מיקל
meikel in terms of how you're valuing people's time, how you're valuing
people's money, whether you're pushing people away from doing the מצווה, mitzvah,
not making it impossible to do the מצווה. mitzvah. So you know,
it's very so you know, it raises the question how could the
גמרא gemara ever make a קל וחומר, kal vechomer, but it's also
very important in terms of attitudinal issues about oh well let's just
play it safe and be מחמיר. machmir. There's a nice תשובה teshuvah
from רבי יהודה הרצל הענקין Rebbi Yehuda Hertzl Henkin in בני בנים
Bnei Banim where he I forget exactly the context, but he sort
of like makes that point as well that almost every חומרא chumra
has קולות kulas associated with it, you can't just assume oh let's
just play it safe and be
מחמיר. machmir. So then he says, וכן בעזרא אמרו אומר, v'chein be-Ezra
amru omer, and this is again to prove that you don't need
the other מינים minim of the לולב, lulav, but this פסוק pasuk
while being brought to prove you don't need the ארבע מינים arba
minim actually is a פסוק pasuk that could be argued to say
why specifically what sort of informs רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's opinion that
you do need the ארבע מינים. arba minim. Because by עזרא Ezra
it says, צאו ההר, tzu ha-har, this is when they made סוכות,
Sukkot, it says go out to the mountain, והביאו עלי זית, ve-heviu
alei zayit, bring olive leaves, ועלי עץ שמן, ve-alei etz shemen, and
oil leaves, which is presumably also like olive, ועלי הדס, ve-alei hadas,
hadas leaves, ועלי תמרים, ve-alei tmarim, and date leaves, ועלי עץ עבות,
ve-alei etz avot, and which is also a type of a הדס,
hadas, לעשות סוכות ככתוב, la'asot sukkot ka-katuv, to make סוכות Sukkot as
it is written. So it sounds there, right, that they're making לולב,
lulav, they're talking about leaves, they're also talking, you know, and they're
making a סוכה! sukkah! So it sounds like they're using these things
to make the סוכה. sukkah. Now, the Rabbis are proving you don't
need ארבע מינים arba minim because of of these things listed, which
one is not of the ארבע מינים? arba minim?
We got olive branch.
Olive. So therefore they say you see, you don't need the ארבע
מינים arba minim today. But it is quite fascinating, the
specifically identifying these things which are so much associated with the לולב
lulav and talking about making them for a סוכה. sukkah. And we
should note that the צדוקים, Tzedukim, trying to remember if it was
the Karaite or the צדוקים Tzedukim or both,
but I'm pretty positive it was the צדוקים Tzedukim in certain Second
Temple texts that said that read the פסוק pasuk ולקחתם לכם ביום
הראשון פרי עץ הדר u-lekachtem lachem ba-yom ha-rishon pri etz hadar means
take for yourself these things, these פרי עץ הדר וכפות תמרים, pri
etz hadar ve-kapot tmarim, and use them to make a סוכה. sukkah.
They understood that it wasn't that there was a מצוה mitzvah of
taking לולב lulav and אתרוג, etrog, ולקחתם לכם u-lekachtem lachem means take
all these things and make your סוכה sukkah with them. And that
was the proof from the verse. Now the question is, and you
know, some scholars want to argue that that might originally have been
how the verse was read, and that might actually be what is
פשט pshat in the verse of of עזרא. Ezra. In fact, it
says נחמיה Nechemia but it's originally it was one ספר sefer עזרא
נחמיה. Ezra Nechemia. Anyway, so if that's true, the one question though
is the עלי זית alei zayit and עלי עץ שמן. alei etz
shemen. What do you do with that? So they argue that well
the you know as we saw earlier, it's not so clear what
the ארבע מינים arba minim were, and that פרי עץ הדר pri
etz hadar could mean olive. Maybe פרי עץ הדר, pri etz hadar,
maybe the, you know, maybe the beautiful tree is the olive tree.
It has fruit and the fruit gives you oil and can so
on, you know, and maybe that's how that was originally interpreted. So
that is the olive wood that's being used here and they read
the verse that way. So that's an interesting possibility and that actually
is what, you know, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says here. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda doesn't deny that there's a מצוה mitzvah of taking the
לולב, lulav, but he actually says, yeah, but he's also actually prepared
to maybe read the verse that way as well. So while this
verse in עזרא Ezra is used as a proof against him because
of the mention of olive, which clearly רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, you
know, believed that פרי עץ הדר pri etz hadar is the אתרוג,
etrog, so he's gonna have to deal with that. Again, it's really
important to recognize the power of this verse as suggesting exactly this
idea, which is רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's idea. So now let's see
what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says back. רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, what
would he respond back to the use of the olive woods? And
obviously he understands that פרי עץ הדר pri etz hadar is an
אתרוג, etrog, not an olive tree. So what does he respond to
that? סבר הני לדפנות. savar hani le-dfanot. Alright, so the olive wood
they used for the walls. But everything else, עלי הדס עלי תמרים
ועלי עץ עבות, alei hadas alei tmarim ve-alei etz avot, לסכך. le-schach.
But the other things they used for the סכך. schach. So רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda really does get his support from here and he
just brackets the issue of the question of the עלי זית. alei
zayit. Okay. So now we know רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's position. Now
why is this interesting? ותנן u-tnan because we taught in another משנה,
Mishnah, מסככין בנסרים. mesachchin be-nesarim. You can make סכך schach with planks.
You might remember that debate, can you use planks? Is it too
much like the roof? דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. That's what
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said. Now here's a problem. How can רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say you could use planks if רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda said you have to use הדס hadas and ערבה aravah and
palm branches? None of those things are planks, right?
Why? You can't make a plank out of that
wood? Out of the trunk?
Thank you. No, forget olive because that's not for he because that
he said is for the wall. We're talking about the סכך. schach.
Right? So to make it out of the trunk of a of
a הדס hadas tree or the trunk of a palm tree. So
thank you, that proves רבא's Rava's point, that if you say you
need to use ארבע מינים, arba minim, it can include from the
trunk of the tree, which is exactly why we're we're quoting this.
So אמר סיב ועיקרא דדיקלא מינא דלולב הוא שמע מינה. amar siv
ve-ikra de-dikla mina de-lulav hu shma mina. You see that the סיב,
siv, which is like some type of a vine around the tree
or whatever, but it's not really the סיב, siv, it's more the
עיקרא דדיקלא, ikra de-dikla, the actual trunk, that's considered to be part
of the ארבע מינים. arba minim. If he demands ארבע מינים arba
minim for the סכך schach and he allows you to use a
plank from the trunk, so the same רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who
demands that you have to be אוגד הלולב oged ha-lulav and אוגדו
במינו ogedo be-mino would not say you actually need to use the
twig. twig of the הדס, hadas, would allow you to use other
parts of the tree as well, that would be included in ארבעה
מינים. arba'ah minim. It's quite fascinating if you think about it, right?
That רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda demands ארבעה מינים arba'ah minim for the
סכך. sechach. He demands ארבעה מינים arba'ah minim to use for the
for the knot around the לולב, lulav, he demands that the לולב
lulav be knotted, so it's quite fascinating the these for the collection
of ideas within רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Okay, yeah.
How do we know that עיקרא ikra means the trunk? Usually, עקרין
akarin are roots.
Yeah, I don't know,
I'm just going by רש"י Rashi and by the context. Okay.
עיקר ikar here I think means like the essence, so the essence
is like the trunk of it. That's the way at least רש"י
Rashi explains it. Okay. Okay, where were we? One minute. Okay, so
we're up. Okay, so
אלמא... alma... okay, שמע מינה. shma mina. וממאמר רבי יהודה ארבעה מינים
אין מידי אחרינא לא? umimamar Rabbi Yehuda arba'ah minim in midi achrina
lo? Now that we mentioned this, let's sort of take a minute
to focus on this fascinating idea. Does he really say you can
only use the four מינים minim for the סכך? sechach? והתניא, vehatanya,
it was taught in a ברייתא: braisa: סיככה בנסרים של ארז, sechachah
binesarim shel erez, if you made the סוכה sukkah with planks of
a cedar, שיש בהן ארבעה טפחים, sheyesh bahen arba'ah tefachim, that had
four
טפחים, tefachim, דברי הכל פסולה, divrei hakol pesulah, then even רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda admits that you can't use planks that wide. אין בהן
ארבעה טפחים, ein bahen arba'ah tefachim, less than four טפחים, tefachim, that's
the debate. You might remember this. רבי מאיר
פוסל ורבי יהודה מכשיר. Rabbi Meir posel veRabbi Yehuda machshir. Then רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says no, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says they're
כשר. kosher. ומודה רבי מאיר, umodeh Rabbi Meir, this is the end
of the ברייתא, braisa, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would concede שאם יש
בין נסר לנסר כמלא נסר, sheim yesh bein neser leneser kimlo neser,
if there's a gap between these planks the same width of the
plank, שמניח פסל ביניהם וכשרה, shemaniach pesal beineihem ukesheirah, then you could
put normal kosher סכך sechach between them and it would be fine.
Anyways, but the point is that we're talking about using planks out
of cedar. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda just got through saying that you
need to use the ארבעה מינים. arba'ah minim. The גמרא Gemara says,
no. מאי ארז הדס. mai erez hadas. When it says ארז, erez,
it's actually talking about a type of a myrtle tree. Now presumably
he doesn't mean that cedar is of the genus myrtle, but presumably
that there is a myrtle tree that is called ארז. erez. כי
הא דרבה בר רב הונא דאמר רבה בר רב הונא אמרי בי
רב עשרה מיני ארזים הם. ki ha deRabbah bar Rav Huna de'amar
Rabbah bar Rav Huna amri bei Rav asarah minei arazim hem. There
are ten species of ארז, erez, שנאמר אתן במדבר ארז שטה והדס.
shenemar eten bamidbar erez shitah vehadas. And then it lists other things.
So you see in this thing, the assumption is that these are
all variations of
ארז. erez. Now again, I'm not exactly sure what the גמרא Gemara
is saying. It maybe is saying that ארז erez and הדס hadas
share the same
botanical classification. But somehow ארז erez either cedar can be understood as
a type of הדס, hadas, which I don't know, if Charles was
here he would tell us already in Wikipedia whether that's true or
not, or it's saying that there is a type of a הדס
hadas that is called ארז. erez. It sounds more like the former,
which is a pretty bold statement. Anyway, okay. But that is the
fascinating position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that you need the ארבעה
מינים arba'ah minim in the לולב, lulav, which actually finds some support
in a פסוק... pasuk... a quasi-support in a פסוק pasuk in עזרא
נחמיה Ezra Nechemiah except with the issue of the עלי. aleh. And
as I say, can actually be a fascinating way of considering reading
the פסוק pasuk itself of ולקחתם לכם. velakachtem lachem. Now we move
on to the next part of the משנה. mishnah. Now that we
understand that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda needs you to use ארבעה מינים
arba'ah minim because it's so so because it's an essential part of
the לולב צריך אגד, lulav tzarich oged, and you can't introduce something
else into the מצוה mitzvah object, that's his logic. But רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says no, you don't need it and רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir also holds a לולב lulav doesn't need an אגד. oged. And
then brings a proof in the משנה mishnah that they used to
use gold chains around the לולב. lulav. To which רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda responded, it would be bound with one of the ארבעה מינים
arba'ah minim below. And now we have a ברייתא braisa that's almost
word for word the end of our משנה. mishnah. תניא, tanya, it
was taught in a ברייתא, braisa, אמר רבי מאיר מעשה ביקירי ירושלים,
amar Rabbi Meir ma'aseh biyakkirei Yerushalayim, the story with some of the
great honored people of Jerusalem, שהיו אוגדין את לולביהן בגימוניות של זהב,
shehayu ogdin es lulaveihen begimuniyos shel zahav,
they would bind their לולבים lulavim with gold bands, and so you
see they did not use the ארבעה מינים. arba'ah minim. אמרו לו,
amru lo, again they is interesting because it's only רבי יהודה's Rabbi
Yehuda position. They said back to him, משם ראיה, misham ra'ayah, there
you want to bring a proof from that? במינו היו אוגדין אותו
מלמטה. bimino hayu ogdin oso milamatah. No, although the gold bands is
what stood out, there was a little knot out of the actual
from one of the ארבעה מינים arba'ah minim at the bottom and
that's what was the knot that counted הלכתית. halachically. The rest was
for aesthetic. Again, pointing out how fascinating it is how much in
מסכת סוכה maseches sukkah you have reference to actual observing actual practices
and then debates of how to interpret what exactly happened. That happens
many many times in מסכת סוכה maseches sukkah much more than it
does in other מסכתות. masechtos. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. אמר ליה רבא להנהו מגדלי הושענא. amar lei Rava lehannu
megadlei hoshana. רבא Rava said to the people that were מגדל הושענא.
migadel hoshana. Now מגדל migadel in this context you might think means
to grow, but actually מגדל migadel can also mean like to braid
or to construct. So those people that make the הושענא Hoshana. *Hoshana*
and הושענא *Hoshana* you'll remember is the name used in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* for like the הדס hadas *Hadass* and the ערבה aravah,
*Arava* and the לולב lulav, *Lulav* as they were bound together, and
the components of the combination of the הדס hadas *Hadass*, לולב lulav
*Lulav*, and ערבה aravah. *Arava*. So those people that would make those,
you know, those bunches and combine it to the לולב lulav *Lulav*.
So what did he say to them? Okay, so he said the
following: דבי ריש גלותא
*Dvei Reish Galusa*, now they did it in the house of the
ריש גלותא *Reish Galusa*. You might remember some interesting stories about the
house of the ריש גלותא *Reish Galusa* on סוכות Sukkot. *Sukkos*. So
they said, he said the following: כי גדליתו הושענא דבי ריש גלותא
*Ki gadlisu hoshana d'bei Reish Galusa*, when you construct the לולבים *lulavim*,
you know, with the הדס hadas, *Hadass* and the ערבה arava *Arava*
in the house of the ריש גלותא *Reish Galusa*, שיירי ביה בית
יד *shari bei beis yad*, leave at the bottom a place to
hold onto it directly. כי היכי ki heichi, דלא תיהוי חציצה chatzitzah
*Ki heichi d'lo tehavi chatzitza*,
so it should not be a חציצה chatzitzah *chatzitza*. Meaning, this is
a very similar to what happens nowadays. They would put some type
of a wrapping around it, maybe imagine they, I don't know, used
a silk thing to wrap around it to combine it. So he
said, you know, let some of that silk thing stick out below,
so when you hold onto the לולב lulav *Lulav*, he can be
directly holding onto the לולב lulav. *Lulav*, הדס hadas *Hadass*, and the
ערבה arava *Arava*. Don't have him hold onto like the silk wrapping
which is holding it all together because then you have a חציצה
chatzitzah. *chatzitza*. So it had to be held directly. Now we have
the issue with, you know, the little what I call the accordion
things, but that's actually using from the ארבע מינים *arba minim* themselves
and we'll discuss that in a minute. But let's first talk about
this. So it says like this, so that's what רבא Rava, *Rava*
said. כי היכי דלא תיהוי חציצה chatzitzah. *Ki heichi d'lo tehavi chatzitza*,
it should not be
an obstacle, a, what's the word? Not obstacle, but
obstruction I guess between the hand and the, and the לולב lulav,
*Lulav*. רבא Rava אמר *Rava amar*, רבא Rava *Rava* said, כל לנאותו
אינו חוצץ kol l'naoso eino chotzetz. *Kol l'naoso eino chotzetz*. Anything that
is there to beautify it is not considered like an extraneous object
and therefore does not create a חציצה chatzitzah *chatzitza*. Now, this is
quite a, you know, I'm going to read another line and then
I'll take a step back for a minute. So that's his argument.
It's not a problem, his position. Okay. Then he said to him:
ואמר רבא ve-amar Rava, *Ve'amar Rava*, רבא Rava *Rava* also said: לא
לינקוט אינש הושענא בסודרא *Lo lincub inish hoshana besudara* דבעינא לקיחה lekicha.
תמה וליכא *d'beina lekicha tamah v'leika*. Now let's say as opposed to
wrapping some silk thing around the לולב lulav *Lulav*, you're actually wrapping
a silk thing around your hand, you're wearing gloves. So,
okay, it says don't, literally he says, don't hold the לולב lulav
*Lulav* with a סודרא *sudara*, with a, like a handkerchief. Okay? But
you could also read it like, you know, don't have gloves on
while you're wearing it. דבעינא לקיחה lekicha, תמה *D'beina lekicha tamah*, you
need actually, you know what? Gloves is not a good example because
I'll explain in a minute. So let's sort of say it means
that let's say have a handkerchief wrapped around the, you know, have
a handkerchief, not handkerchief, but yeah, like yeah, have some type of
a cloth wrapped around the לולב lulav, *Lulav* and don't take it
via the cloth.
It's not something that fits on your hand.
Well, yeah, תוספות tosafot *Tosfos* has a discussion about that, but for
now, let's say the other way, that you have the handkerchief wrapped
around the לולב lulav *Lulav* and don't take the לולב lulav. *Lulav*
via the handkerchief. דבעינא לקיחה תמה *D'beina lekicha tamah*, you need a
full taking, which means to take it directly, not indirectly. וליכא *V'leika*,
you don't have it. רבא Rava אמר *Rava amar*, רבא Rava *Rava*
says, לקיחה על ידי דבר אחר l'kichah al yedei davar acher. שמה
לקיחה *Lekicha al yedei davar acher shma lekicha*. Even if you take
something indirectly, it's considered that you took it. So I want to
read this proof and then I want to go back and unpack
a little what we just said. אמר רבא Rava *Amar Rava*, so
רבא Rava *Rava* said, מנא אמינא לה *Mina amina la*, how do
I know that taking something indirectly is considered like taking? דלקיחה על
ידי דבר אחר al yedei davar acher. שמה לקיחה *D'lekicha al yedei
davar acher shma lekicha*, that taking something indirectly is considered taking. דתניא
*Dtanya*, we taught in the משנה mishna. *mishna*: אזוב ezov. כיצד *Eizov
ketzad*, you have a hyssop. Now you would dip the אזוב *eizov*
into a tube, like sort of like a, you know, an eyelash
applicator tube, a thin tube you would stick the אזוב *eizov* in
and in that tube would be the water and the ashes of
the פרה אדומה parah adumah. *Parah Adumah*. And that's how you would
transport the ashes of the פרה אדומה parah adumah *Parah Adumah* to
different towns, is they would be in these applicator tubes and in
those tubes, you know, that would sort of protect them, it wouldn't
spill, and be a small amount and you'd open it up, you'd
stick in your אזוב *eizov* and you'd splash it on the people.
That's how you would do for the פרה *parah* process. ושבצרת *U'shaveres*,
so let's say your אזוב *eizov*, your hyssop, is has a very
short stem, it snapped, okay? And you really need to do it
now, you can't go looking for more אזוב *eizov*, what are you
going to do? You can't get it into the tube, you know,
you can't get it all the way down to get the water.
So what are you going to do? So it says, מספקו בחוט
*Metapko bechut*, so you satisfy it, meaning you extend it with a
string, ובכוש *uv'kush*, or like with a spindle, some type of an
extra twig you attach to it, וטובל ומעלה *ve'tovel v'ma'aleh*, and you
dip it into the tube and you pull it out of the
tube with the string, ואוחז באזוב *v'ochez be'eizov*, and then you hold
onto the hyssop and you sprinkle. Okay, but fine, it's nice that
you're holding directly to the hyssop when you're doing the sprinkling, but
when you put it in the tube, you didn't put it in
directly, you put it in through with the help of a string.
So אמאי, amai, why is that כשר? kosher? ולקח וטבל אמר רחמנא,
v'lakach v'taval amar rachmana, it says you shall take the hyssop and
dip it. So you're not directly taking the hyssop and dipping it,
you're only taking it indirectly with the help of the string. So
אמר אלא לאו שמע מינה לקיחה על ידי דבר אחר שמה לקיחה,
amar ela lav shma mina l'kichah al yedei davar acher sh'ma l'kichah,
you see that even though you took the hyssop not directly, but
you took it and dipped it with the string, that's fine, that's
considered like taking it. רש"י Rashi says so then why do you
have to hold onto the hyssop directly when you sprinkle? He says
that's just to get like accuracy, you know, to get control, try
sprinkling it holding onto the string. You want to sprinkle it directly
on the person. But fundamentally, even though you took it by the
string, you're okay. So the גמרא Gemara says ממאי, mimai, how do
you know that? דילמא שאני התם, dilma shani hatam, maybe there it's
different. כיון דחבריה כגופיה דמי. kivan d'chavreih k'gufeih dami.
Since you've attached the string to the actual hyssop, it becomes like
the hyssop itself. But if you took something without attaching it, imagine
for example you took some tongs and you used the tongs to
pick up the לולב, lulav right, and the הדס hadas and the
ערבה, arava, but you didn't attach it, you can't say it's now
part of the לולב lulav and the הדס hadas and the ערבה.
arava. Okay, so therefore, or let's say you made with this handkerchief,
let's say you sort of made you know a holder. But okay,
let's say you sort of made like
a holder, okay, and then you put them in the holder. So
they're not it's not attached, you know, it's not like one unit
with the לולב lulav and the הדס, hadas but you're taking it
by lifting up the holder, that's how you're taking it. So that
maybe is different, that maybe is not considered a taking. Says the
גמרא Gemara אלא מהכא, ela mehacha, from here, another example from the
case of the פרה אדומה. נפלה משפופרת לשוקת, nafla mishfoperet l'shoket,
let's say from a משפופרת mishfoperet that contained not the mixture of
the ashes and the water but just the ashes. And you're supposed
to pour from this משפופרת mishfoperet with the ashes into a trough
or into like a vessel that has the water of the פרה
אדומה in it and you do the mixing that makes it into
the water that you can use. But instead of pouring from the
משפופרת mishfoperet of the ashes, some ashes accidentally spilled out into the
vessel with the water. So פסול, pasul, that's invalid, because it says
you have to directly through intentional human agency pour the ashes, not
just it accidentally you know happens indirectly or unintentionally. So the גמרא
Gemara says הא, ha, so from that we can infer הפילו הוא,
hepilo hu, if you intentionally tipped the you know poured the ashes
in, כשר, kasher, it's כשר, kosher, even though you didn't touch the
ashes, you just poured it in by holding onto the משפופרת. mishfoperet.
אמאי, why is that כשר? kosher? ולקחו ונתנו, v'lakchu v'natnu,
it says you shall take the ashes and place them into the
water אמר רחמנא. amar rachmana. And you didn't place them, you didn't
take them, you only took them because they were in the משפופרת.
mishfoperet. So אלא לאו שמע מינה לקיחה על ידי דבר אחר שמה
לקיחה, ela lav shma mina l'kichah al yedei davar acher sh'ma l'kichah,
you hear from here
that taking something indirectly is considered to be like taking it.
It sounds like a כח דגברא. koach d'gavra. What? It sounds like
it's כח גברא, koach gavra, like force. Yes.
But now here is the question. There's a lot of questions to
ask. So we have basically רבא, Rava רבה Rabbah not liking either
of these things, taking them with something that interferes and taking it
indirectly. And רבא Rava accepts both of them. So there's a חציצה
chatzitzah and לקיחה על ידי דבר אחר. l'kichah al yedei davar acher
So there's two questions to ask here. Well one question is just
to clarify something, which is I was waiting for somebody to ask,
he says wait a minute Rabbi Lonstein I don't understand, how if
you said that you know when if if you said that
if רבה Rabbah first said that there's a חציצה chatzitzah. when you
have I don't know the silk thing in the way, then how
is that any different than saying that oh don't take it with
this handle because it's לקיחה על ידי דבר אחר l'kichah al yedei
davar acher and that's no good? Who needs this לקיחה על ידי
דבר אחר lekichah al yedei davar acher reason? You know, there's a
חציצה. chatzitzah? The thing he just got through saying that you have
to touch it directly. Why is there this separate discussion, right? So
what's that point? Why I mean if he already said it's פסול
pasul because there's an obstruction, why should this be different? So there's
a long תוספות tosafot that tries to figure this out. The basic
conclusion of תוספות Tosafot is fascinating, it's the following. It's like question
is if I am trying to hold the לולב lulav directly and
like I'm saying I'm not sort of I'm not saying I'm taking
it with something, I'm holding it with my hand, but there's something
in between, it's wrapped up in a piece of silk. So that
is an issue about the way I'm taking it is directly with
my hand, there that piece of silk that's there could be considered
to be a חציצה. chatzitzah. And that's the first point he makes.
If you're not directly touching it because the act you're taking is
to take it directly, then there's a חציצה chatzitzah, problem. But let's
say I say I'm not trying to take it directly, I'm not
trying to hold onto it, I'm trying to lift it up with
this like holder. Okay? So somewhat maybe ironically, but since you're defining
your act differently, it would theoretically be able to say that in
the first case it's a חציצה chatzitzah. because if you want to
hold on to it, you're not holding on to it. There's something
between your hand and the לולב. lulav Whereas the second case isn't
a problem because the second case, I'm not trying to hold on
to it. I'm just trying to take it with something, to use
something to pick it up. So if I'm using that thing, you
know, here's another way of thinking about it. If I'm using the
handle, the way the גמרא Gemara says that when you tie it
to the
hyssop, it becomes part of the hyssop. Well, if I use something
with my hand, like I use tongs, so what if I'm using
tongs, conceptually you can see those tongs as what? An extension of
my hand. So maybe if I try to hold it directly and
there's something in between, that's a חציצה. chatzitzah. But if I had
to pick it up with the tongs, maybe the tongs are like
part extension of my hand and there's no... so if there was
a piece of silk between the tongs and the לולב, lulav that
would be a problem. But maybe I can... it's okay because once
if I'm using the tongs, the tongs are part of my hand.
And there רבה Rabbah says no, that's not good either. לקיחה על
ידי דבר אחר lekichah al yedei davar acher. is not good. To
which רבא Rava responds and he says it is good. Now רבא
Rava says, the first point רבא Rava said I said is if
it's there to beautify it, כל לנאותו אינו חוצץ.
kol l'na'oto
eino chotzetz, Okay?
If it's there to beautify. Now the tongs aren't beautifying it. So
why do I think it's okay to use the tongs? They're not
beautifying it. Why isn't that a חציצה? chatzitzah So that's a different
point. If you're using the tongs, they're not just there in between,
then they become part of your hand and they become an extension
of you. So these are two different ideas. Directly taking it with
something in between, רבה Rabbah says no good, חציצה. chatzitzah רבא Rava
says if it's there to beautify, it's not considered an obstruction. And
then indirectly taking it and using something to take it, and there
רבה Rabbah says that also... רבה Rabbah says it also doesn't do
you any good. And רבא Rava says that's also fine, even though
it's not to beautify it, here it's acting as a way of
taking, an indirect way of taking and that's also okay. Yes. So
like according to רבא you have to say the ברכה berakhah before
you pick your לולב lulav, out of the bag and your אתרוג
etrog out of your box? Well, picking the לולב lulav out of
the bag, that's an excellent example of this idea of לקיחה על
ידי דבר אחר. lekichah al yedei davar acher. Because the bag is
certainly not לנאותו, l'naoso, certainly doesn't make it look any bigger, better,
but you actually are taking it על ידי דבר אחר. al yedei
davar acher. You're picking it up על ידי דבר אחר. al yedei
davar acher. So you know that's an excellent point. One question could
be what your כוונה kavanah is, but if you don't have any
כוונה, kavanah, if you had specific כוונה kavanah not to be יוצא...
yotze... You know, it's a really good question.
I mean the basic difference is that we is that you're not
doing it דרך גדילתו, derech gedilaso, the
normal way it grows, right? The same way you hold the אתרוג
etrog upside down and then you make the ברכה. berakhah. But if
you let's say are, depends on how you're holding it, right? If
you let's say are holding your bag up, most people will hold
their bag vertical because they don't want it to bump into things
and you need to walk and get around. So you're holding it
naturally, you're holding it על ידי דבר אחר. al yedei davar acher.
I guess you just have to be really careful not to hold
the אתרוג etrog in the box, to turn the box, if you're
holding the לולב, lulav for a moment you turn your box. It's
an excellent point, really. Now we will find out that even if
you were יוצא yotze already you can still according to ראשונים Rishonim
make the ברכה berakhah if you haven't yet done the נענועים. nanuim.
But, you know, most people wouldn't want to wait, you know, until
before making the ברכה. berakhah. It's really an excellent point and I'm
curious if some פוסקים poskim sort of make that point. I don't
remember seeing that discussion. But that's a great example of the idea
of לקיחה על ידי דבר אחר. lekichah al yedei davar acher Because
that's exactly what you're doing. You're carrying your לולב lulav על ידי
דבר אחר.
Nobody is saying
it's לנאותו, l'naoso, but that's a way of taking something if
you take it through something else. Yes. It's just this concept of
לקיחה על ידי דבר אחר lekichah al yedei davar acher, sounds to
me like a similar logic in the סוגיא sugya in שבת Shabbat
of קיטע יוצא בשבת, kite'a yotze b'shabbat, that similar that the faux
leg's an extension of the person or something else. Yeah, but that's
also because it's attached to the person and it can be an
extension. This more focuses not on your physical body but on your
action. Like, you know, it's like when you're doing an act of
taking and you're using something to do the act, you know, sort
of like in that act it's considered to be an extension of
you, but not more of an ongoing way. So there is some
similarity, but this is very much act-focused, right? That's why לקיחה על
ידי דבר אחר, I'm
taking it through something and that is a way of taking something.
Yes.
But
when he's using some sort of an extension, at the end of
the day, he still takes it directly.
Right, so there's nothing between him and the לולב.
lulav, But he uses the extension to get it out. Even when
he's talking about, he says וזוקפו בחודי כוש v'zokfo b'chudei chush וטובל
מלמעלה v'tovel milma'alah ואוחז באזוב ומזה. v'ochez ba'ezov u'mazeh. At
the end of the day, he still takes the אזוב.
Oh, no, רש"י Rashi says that's only so that you don't... so
that you have control over it.
Control. But the fact that... but that's what רש"י Rashi says. He
still eventually takes it with his hand.
Yes but that doesn't address, but that's not necessary for the act
of dipping. The act of dipping is a separate requirement and according
and that you never took it directly and that's okay.
Is it the dipping that
they're supposed to have contact? Each one is a separate- no, each
one is a separate requirement. So if there's a requirement- otherwise the
גמרא Gemara, wouldn't have a proof. The whole point is that even
for the dipping there was never a direct taking and even so
it's okay. So that's now the other point I wanted to make
is, when we say something like כל לנאותו אינו חוצץ, kol l'na'oto
eino chotzetz? or there's another discussion that תוספות Tosafot, brings down which
is מין במינו אינו חוצץ. min b'mino eino chotzetz. If it's a
similar type, it's not חוצץ. chotzetz. It says, like תוספות, Tosafot like
when do we say that? For example, let's say I go into
the מקוה mikvah or one goes into the מקוה mikvah and her
friend is holding very tightly onto her hand, right, and no water
can get through. Well would we say like מין במינו אינו חוצץ?
min b'mino eino chotzetz? Or let's say, you know, she's wearing some
beautiful things. Would you say כל לנאותו kol l'na'oto, אינו חוצץ? Now,
and you know תוספות Tosafot, tries
to figure out when we say some of these principles, when we
don't. Obviously sometimes, like if you're thinking about the idea of going
to the מקוה, mikvah, you think much more there's a real need
for something to be in contact. And therefore if there's a need
to be in contact to say well if it's to beautify it's
not a חציצה, chatzitzah? if it's the same thing it's not a
חציצה. chatzitzah? Like, okay, but bottom line there's no direct contact between
the body and the water. We might not- those- those arguments might
not carry weight. If however there's a- here, you know, you could
challenge this whole idea of why are we discussing חציצה. chatzitza The
תורה Torah never said, you know, the לולב lulav has to touch
your flesh. It just says you should take, so I took it.
Whoever said that it has to mean it has to physically touch
my body? So here that might be why we have sort of,
you know, we're more forgiving of חציצות chatzitzot because the real question
we're asking ourselves is not is the לולב lulav touching your body.
The real question we're asking ourselves is is it considered like you
took it. Is it direct enough that you took it? And if
there's something that's obstructing, maybe it's not like considered a direct taking.
You know, maybe it's not considered like you took it because your
direct act was interrupted with something else. So there we could say,
you know, it's there to beautify it, it's מינו, mino, it's not
really is considered to be something that sort of obstructs the act,
gets in the way. But again, it's interesting to try to figure
out when do we have more forgiving sort of criteria for חציצה
chatzitza. and consider these ideas of like it's not such an obstruction,
it's not such a foreign matter. And when sometimes is that not
like relevant? So if you just look at the last line of
תוספות, Tosafot, he says, the first well, the first of the widest
lines of תוספות, Tosafot he says like this: he says a similar
question about סיב siv and his last four words of the תוספות
Tosafot? כי היכי, the end of the first wide line he says
ואין לדמות כל הדברים. v'ein l'damot kol had'varim. Okay, do you see
it? You see those last four words of the big first line
of תוספות? Tosafot It's right before the דיבור המתחיל dibur hamatchil מין
במינו. min b'mino. He says on ל״ז עמוד א׳. lamed zayin amud
aleph. He says ואין לדמות כל הדברים. v'ein l'damot kol had'varim. Like
he tries to figure out sometimes we say these principles, כל לנאותו,
מין במינו, min b'mino, sometimes we don't say them. Yeah, yeah, there's
somehow you got to figure out some difference between the cases. But
I do think to the degree that there's starts with a concept
of ורחץ בשרו במים v'rachatz besaro bamayim is a concept of your
body has to be touching it. Right, or like by the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash we discussed an idea that there can't be a
חציצה chatzitza. between the feet of the כהנים kohanim and the floor
and that's because somehow the physical connection to the floor is part
of the קדושה kedusha of the כהנים, kohanim, you know, and being
connected to the ground of the מקדש. Mikdash. As opposed to
here, you know, if we hadn't learned this גמרא, Gemara you would
have said like whoever said anything about חציצה? chatzitza. Why did that
be even a relevant category here? It doesn't say it should touch
your flesh, right? So okay, but maybe certain חציצות chatzitzot would say
you didn't really take it, you didn't take it directly, you didn't
take it in an unobstructed manner. But that we can be more
forgiving in terms of what is and is not defined as an
obstruction.
Yeah, but it's-
let's turn the conceptual corner. This is another piece of the vocabulary
that you've been constructing all along, that the גמרא's Gemara got an
inclination to see the סוכה Sukkah in מקדש Mikdash terminology.
A bit of חציצה? chatzitza Even now en passant in your thinking
out loud.
No, but that's true although I mention מקוה, mikvah, but that also
is מקדש.
Mikdash. In other words, all of a
sudden חציצות chatzitzot come up in so many contexts but I hear
the point.
It's a טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah.
It is- it is a context that comes up a lot in
מקדש Mikdash and in taking things
and whatever. That's interesting. I hadn't thought about
that. I think it's a piece of that whole the way the
גמרא Gemara abstracts סוכה. Sukkah. I hear that. That's an interesting point.
דאמר רבה, de-amar Rabba, רבה Rabba says, לא רדיז איניש
לולבא בהושענא, lo
raduz inish
lulava be-Hoshana,
you should not go ahead and have your like הדס hadas and
ערבה arava bunch, you know, wrapped together and then stick your לולב
lulav into it. Okay, you know, sometimes we do that, but we
can do it because we have those accordion things
so it doesn't rub up against it. But imagine you just had
the הדס hadas and ערבה arava tied together in some type of
thing and you crammed your לולב lulav. into it. So why? דאמר
רבה, de-amar Rabba, wherever, דדילמא
נטרי
טרפי והוי חציצה, de-dilma natri tarfei ve-havei chatzitza, some leaves will come
off of the הדס hadas and ערבה, arava, והוי חציצה, ve-havei chatzitza,
and then they will be a חציצה between you and trying to
hold directly onto the הדס hadas
and ערבה. Arava, You'll have some torn off הדס hadas leaves that
will be between your hand and the actual הדס hadas and לולב
Lulav that's still kosher. ורבא אמר, ve-Rava amar, and רבא says, מין
במינו אינו חוצץ. min be-mino eino chotzetz. I jumped ahead, I mentioned
that. If it's all הדס hadas leaves and ערבה Arava, leaves and
לולב Lulav leaves, they're not really foreign matter and therefore even if
they're not attached to the לולב, Lulav they're not a חציצה. Another
more forgiving concept about what types of things are considered foreign matter
and a חציצה. By the way, it's worth noting that he doesn't
say that if you tear off הדס hadas, and ערבה arava leaves,
it'll be פסול. pasul. We never really said explicitly how many leaves
have to fall off for it to become פסול. pasul. We talked
about the leaves falling off, right? But we never sort of, you
know, went, there's a lot of discussion by the הדס hadas
about that, you know, about like three fresh leaves at the top,
etc., but we never actually explicitly, you know, said how many leaves.
So this is interesting that he acknowledges that some leaves can come
off and it can still be כשר. kosher. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues. ואמר רבה, ve-amar Rabba,
רבה Rabba also said, לא ליגוז איניש לולבא בהושענא. lo ligoz inish
lulava be-Hoshana.
You have your לולב Lulav wrapped up in your הדס hadas and
ערבה, arava that's the הושענא. And now you figure your לולב Lulav
is too big, don't cut it shorter at the bottom, right? You
know that's how you can shorten your לולב Lulav because you just
cut it shorter and you have a new bottom. So don't do
that. Why? דמשתרי הוצא והוי חציצה, de-mishtari hutza ve-havei chatzitza,
because what happens when you cut the bottom of your לולב, Lulav,
right? The leaves that are attached at the very bottom are now
no longer attached. Like everybody sort of knows how a לולב Lulav
is constructed, yes? So you know, like I still don't have my
things anyway, it's got all of these overlapping leaves that are coming
in at different junction points, right, at the bottom. So if you
cut off, you know, two inches at the bottom, all those connection
points at the bottom are now separated and free leaves. Okay, so
he's now got his same problem. Now you got לולב lulav leaves
that are in your way. והוי חציצה. ve-havei chatzitza. Okay, ורבא אמר
מין במינו אינו חוצץ,
ve-Rava
amar
min be-mino eino chotzetz, the same
point, I don't care that you got לולב lulav, leaves there, they're
not a חציצה. ואמר רבא, Ve'amar Rava.
רבא also says, הדס של מצוה אסור להריח בו. hadas shel mitzvah
assur le-hariach bo. Now we're getting beyond חציצה issues. הדס של מצוה,
hadas shel mitzvah,
you can't smell the הדס hadas of the מצוה mitzvah that you're
using in your לולב. lulav אתרוג של מצוה מותר להריח בו, etrog
shel mitzvah mutar le-hariach bo, but the אתרוג etrog you can smell
it. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? הדס לריחא קאי, hadas
le-reicha kai, הדס, Hadas the reason
people, the fundamental use of a הדס Hadas when it's not used
for a מצוה mitzvah is to smell it. So כי אקצייה, ki
aktzyei, when it is, that's the same word as מוקצה, muktzah, when
it's
set aside, meaning there's an idea of הוקצה למצותו, huktza le-mitzvato, something
that is a מצוה mitzvah object set aside for the מצוה mitzvah
is considered off-limits for other things, even if you're not taking it
away from the מצוה. mitzvah. You can smell it, it doesn't detract
from the מצוה, mitzvah, but it's considered to be like fully designated,
set aside for the מצוה. mitzvah. So מריחא אקצייה, me-reicha aktzyei, so
the way it's sort of designated is its fundamental central identity. So
since the central identity of a הדס Hadas or function is to
smell it, when we say this הדס Hadas is set aside fully
for the מצוה, mitzvah, it means don't smell it. It's no longer
here for
your use, it's given over to the מצוה mitzvah use, don't smell
it because its use is smelling. אתרוג לאכילה קאי, etrog le-achila kai,
אתרוג etrog that basically what do you do with an אתרוג etrog
during the rest of the year? You eat it. So כי אקצייה
מאכילה אקצייה. ki aktzyei me-achila aktzyei. They say don't eat the אתרוג
etrog now for סוכות. Sukkot, It's set aside for מצוה mitzvah use,
not for your use. So my use means what I would normally
use it for, I can't use it. Don't eat it. But yes,
smell it. That's an incidental benefit that's not its primary identity and
that's not made off-limits. Now you might tell me what about the
whole case before about רב חנינא Rav Chanina that dipped her? The
גמרא Gemara is going to discuss that. Don't worry. The גמרא Gemara
will later discuss those issues, but for now that's the הלכה. halacha.
Now, by the way, getting back to the point that דב Dov
raised about this whole idea of מקדש, Mikdash, etc., you know, this
idea of הוקצה למצותו huktza le-mitzvato applies in many cases, but it
particularly was underscored by סוכה Sukkah by this idea of the סכך
sechach where it says you קרא שם שמים על הסכך Kara Shem
Shamayim Al HaSechach וחג הסוכות להשם, V'Chag HaSukkot Lashem,
God's name is like על הסוכה, Al HaSukkah, the גמרא Gemara. actually
says, and that makes the סכך Sechach off-limits, and we talked about
the נוי סוכה Noi Sukkah off-limits. So רשי Rashi here, רשי Rashi
here couldn't have just invoked a general principle of הוקצה למצוותו, Huktza
Lemitzvato, but רשי Rashi actually invokes that specific סוכה Sukkah principle. If
you look at רשי, Rashi, the word that says אסור להריח בו
Asur Le'ariach Bo at about twenty lines down in the narrow lines,
רשי Rashi says דגמרינן מסוכה דילפינן בפרק קמא דחל שם שמים על
עצי סוכה ואסירי בהנאה כל שבעה
והוה הוקצה למצוה. De-gamrinan mi-sukkah de-yalfinan be-perek kama de-chal shem shamayim al
atzei sukkah ve-asiri be-hana'ah kol shiva ve-havei huktza le-mitzvah. So רשי Rashi
says this is not a general principle of הוקצה למצוותו, Huktza Lemitzvato,
it's specific to סוכה Sukkah and it applies to לולב lulav, as
well. So that also again sort of is reinforcing this much more
היימיש, Heimish, God-present concept that we are using here. Okay, so now
back to the גמרא. Gemara, ואמר רבא. Ve'amar Rava. Now רבא also
said, and now this case that רבא's going to talk about is
not on סוכות, it's just contrasting הדס Hadas to אתרוג Etrog during
the rest of the year, like on a שבת. Shabbat. Okay, any
שבת Shabbat of the year. הדס במחובר, Hadas Bimchubar, you have myrtle
growing on a tree and it's you know שבת Shabbat I don't
know in January, okay, so מותר להריח בו, Mutar Le'ariach Bo, you
can smell it on שבת, Shabbat, we're not afraid that if you
smell it off of the tree you're going to come to break
off a twig. אתרוג במחובר אסור להריח בו. Etrog Bimchubar Asur Le'ariach
Bo. An אתרוג Etrog you can't smell an אתרוג Etrog off of
a tree, you can't smell an apple while it's growing from a
tree on שבת. Shabbat. מאי טעמא, Mai Ta'ama, why? הדס דלהריח קאי,
Hadas Dile'ariach Ka'ei, הדס hadas the whole point is to smell it.
שרי ליה לא אתי למגזייה. Sharei Lei Lo Ati Lemigzyei. So you
let me smell it, I'm not going to cut it off. Why
do I need to cut it off? You just let me smell
it. Maybe I want to bring it home and have my wife
smell it, but okay, I'm getting the benefit I want right now.
I'm not going to willfully violate and I'm not going to forget,
it's not like I'll get caught up because I'm doing exactly what
I want to be doing. However, אתרוג דלאכילה קאי, Etrog De'achilah Ka'ei,
where the אתרוג's Etrog whole purpose is eating and my focus is
on eating, אי שרית ליה, Ei Shreit Lei, if you let me
smell it I'd say ah smells so good, I'd love to take
a bite, and then אתי למגזייה, Ati Lemigzyei, you'll come to cut
it off. ותרא האשה כי טוב העץ למאכל, Vatere Ha'ishah Ki Tov
Ha'etz L'ma'achal, right? You start smelling it and then you want to
actually take a bite. There's actually an opinion that the tree that
the חטא של אדם וחוה Chet Shel Adam VeChava was the אתרוג,
Etrog, the עץ הדעת Etz HaDa'at was the אתרוג. Etrog. Anyway, so
רשי Rashi has a question. רשי Rashi says but maybe you won't
pluck it off the tree, maybe you'll be smelling it and you'll
just take a bite while it's attached to the tree. So רשי
Rashi says אין לך תלוש גדול מזה, Ein Lecha Talush Gadol Mizeh,
that's also a שבת Shabbat prohibition of detaching something. Who cares if
you detached it by plucking it or you detached it by taking
a bite out of it? You still detached a growing thing from
the tree. ושינוי הוא? Veshinui Hu? Not the normal way you take
it off of a tree. All right, I don't know. Okay, anyway,
that was another related issue about the difference between הדס hadas and
ערבה, applied to הדס hadas, and אתרוג Etrog applied to a שבת
הלכה. Shabbat Halakha. ואמר רבא. Now רבא also says, לולב בימין ואתרוג
בשמאל. Lulav Biyamin Ve'etrog Bismoal. לולב lulav, you take in your right
hand, the
אתרוג Etrog
in your left. For
lefties like me, we פסקן Pasken that it's the reverse, it's your
strong
hand, so lefties would take the
לולב lulav? in the left. But
anyway, assuming a world of righties, לולב
lulav. in the right hand,
אתרוג Etrog in the
left. מאי טעמא,
Mai Ta'ama, what's the reason? הני תלת מצות והאי חדא
מצוה. Hanei Telat Mitzvot Ve'hai Chada Mitzvah. The לולב lulav. is three
מצות, Mitzvot, three parts of it, three-quarters of the מצוה, Mitzvah, and
the אתרוג Etrog is only one. By the way, notice in all
of these discussions, even though we don't פסקן Pasken like ר' יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda that לולב צריך אגד, Lulav Tzarich Agad, all of these
discussions assume you're doing an אגד Agad anyway. You're having the לולב,
הדס, וערבה, Lulav, Hadas, Ve'arava, right? When רבא says don't, you know
רבא says sticking it into the הדס and the ערבה, cutting it
when it's already in the bunch, all of these assume that even
if it doesn't strictly require the אגד, Agad, it's coming together knotted
together. So you have a knotted together לולב, הדס, וערבה, Lulav, Hadas,
Ve'arava, that's three out of four, that goes in your stronger hand,
that goes in the right hand. Okay.
אמר ליה ר' ירמיה לר' זריקא. Amar Lei Rebbi Yirmiya LeRebbi Zerika.
ר' ירמיה Rebbi Yirmiya said to ר' זריקא, Rebbi Zerika, מאי טעמא
לא מברכינן אלא על נטילת לולב? Mai Ta'ama Lo Mevarchinan Ela Al
Netilat Lulav? Why do we say על נטילת לולב? Al Netilat Lulav?
Why don't we say על נטילת ארבע מינים Al Netilat Arba Minim
or על נטילת פרי עץ הדר כפות תמרים וענף עץ עבות וערבי
נחל? Al Netilat Peri Etz Hadar Kapot Temarim Ve'anaf Etz Avot Ve'arvei
Nachal? So why don't we say that? So he says הוא דגבוה
מכולם. Hu Degavo'a Mikulam. Yeah, because לולב lulav? is bigger, so it
stands out and therefore when people look at it, they focus on
the לולב, lulav that sort of dominates the לולב lulav? with everything
else. So then the גמרא, Gemara so he says וליגבהיה לאתרוג ולברך.
Veligbeihye Le'etrog Ulevarech. So he just assumed it meant it happened to
be more visible, so why not hold up the אתרוג Etrog real
high and say על נטילת אתרוג, Al Netilat Etrog, you know? So
ר' ירמיה, Rebbi Yirmiya, yeah ר' ירמיה Rebbi Yirmiya liked asking those
questions, that's true. אמר ליה הוא במינו גבוה
מכולם. Amar Lei Hu Bemino Gavo'a Mikulam. It's naturally bigger than all
of them, okay, and therefore obviously that gives it more dominance and
therefore you're going to make that ברכה. Berakha. I'll use this opportunity
to just mention another fascinating הלכה Halakha that we said, I think,
at the end of one דף, Daf, but we didn't have enough
time to sit on it for a minute, which is, you know
the גמרא Gemara you might remember has this idea of לקיחת תמה...
Lekichat Tamah... That they all have to be, or the ארבעה מינים
שבלולב מעכבים זה את זה. arba'ah minim shebalulav me'akvim zeh et zeh.
You know, you need all four of them to be יוצא. yotze.
But there's an interesting position of the גאונים Geonim that the רמב"ם
Rambam פוסק, paskens, which actually is, you need all four of them
to be יוצא yotze but you don't have to take them at
the same time. You could take a לולב lulav in the morning,
an אתרוג esrog in the afternoon, the הדס two hours later, the
ערבה an hour later. No, we don't פוסק pasken like רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. Okay, now that's בדיעבד bedi'eved not לכתחילה, l'chatchila, but you
can be יוצא yotze if you eventually took the ארבעה מינים, arba'ah
minim, it wasn't one act of לקיחה. תוספות Tosafot argues, תוספות Tosafot,
says if the תורה Torah says one act of taking, you can't
take them at separate times. But within the רמב"ם Rambam that says
that you could take them separately, he says and when you take
the לולב, lulav. you make the
ברכה bracha על נטילת al netilat or על לקיחת al lekichat כפות
תמרים. kapot tmarim. And then when you take the אתרוג, esrog, you
say על נטילת al netilat or I forget, על לקיחת, al lekichat,
you know, פרי עץ הדר. pri etz hadar. And he says you
would make each one a different ברכה. bracha.
נטילת, netilat, that's the rabbinic formulation.
Right, נטילה netila is like לקיחה, right. Right, and then when you
got to the הדס it'd be על לקיחת, al lekichat, you know,
ענף עץ עבות. anaf etz avot. נטילת netilat or whatever, ענף עץ
עבות. anaf etz avot. So it's quite interesting since we're mentioning here
a ברכה bracha and that the לולב lulav dominates, and that's that
idea that it's one act of taking. A, according to רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda you literally have to bunch the לולב, lulav הדס, and
ערבה and make them one unit, but even if we and we
practically do it even if you don't have to, but certainly we
sort of see it as one taking dominated by the לולב, lulav
whereas again, the debate of רמב"ם Rambam versus תוספות, Tosafot גאונים Geonim
versus תוספות Tosafot. is, can you בדיעבד bedi'eved be יוצא yotze with
four separate acts of taking? And as long as you did all
four acts somehow you would be יוצא, yotze, yeah.
I'm interested in something else, is the רמב"ם Rambam deriving what those
ברכות brachot would be because they're not?
Yeah, I think he's, I don't know if he's getting it from
tradition of the גאונים Geonim or he's just speculating. A lot of
the ברכות brachot are not in the גמרא Gemara, and were finally
crystallized in the גאונים Geonic period. So I don't know though if
there was a if there were גאונים Geonim pre you know so
that
principle of not making a ברכה bracha that's not there really extends
through the גאונים Geonic period. In other words, you're not supposed to
make a ברכה bracha that's
You mean develop new ברכות? brachot? Yeah. Yeah, so I mean again,
you know, mostly a lot of it was crystallized in the גאונים
Geonic period and there's some discussion sometimes in the ראשונים Rishonim about
the possibility but mostly it stops with the גאונים. Geonim. Okay, let's
take a look now at the next משנה. mishna. היכן
היו מנענעין? heichan hayu menani'in?
Where would you shake the לולב? lulav Now it's so funny, we
didn't even mention the act of taking the לולב. I mean, you
know, we didn't say you have to lift it up and take
it. I mean, that was just discussed in the גמרא, Gemara right,
about taking and taking with an obstacle, but it wasn't discussed in
the משנה. mishna משנה Mishnah, just goes straight to shaking the לולב.
Okay, so where would you shake the לולב? So it says, בהודו
לה' תחילה וסוף. be'Hodu laShem techila v'sof. By הודו לה' Hodu laShem
beginning and end. Beginning and end means the הודו לה' Hodu laShem
that occurs in the middle of הלל Hallel and the הודו לה'
Hodu laShem at the end of הלל. Hallel. רש"י Rashi points out
that people aren't aware of this, but in תהלים Tehillim it's really
all one פרק. perek. So,
right?
So we have right, we have the right. It says here if
you look at the top, right, it says תהלים קי"ז. Tehillim kuf
yud zayin. הללו את ה' כל גוים, Halelu et Hashem kol goyim,
הודו לה' כי טוב, Hodu laShem ki tov, יאמר נא, yomar na,
right?
And all of that, and then again here at the very end,
right, הודו לה' כי טוב כי לעולם חסדו. Hodu laShem ki tov
ki l'olam chasdo. And it's all in, if you look here at
the back, that has your תהלים, Tehillim, so קי"ז kuf yud zayin
is הללו את ה' כל גוים. Halelu et Hashem kol goyim. קי"ח
kuf yud chet is
הודו לה' כי טוב כי לעולם
חסדו,
Hodu laShem ki tov ki
l'olam chasdo, יאמר נא ישראל כי לעולם חסדו, yomar na Yisrael ki
l'olam chasdo, יאמר נא בית אהרן כי לעולם חסדו, yomar na veit
Aharon ki l'olam chasdo, יאמר נא יראי ה' כי לעולם חסדו, yomar
na yirei Hashem ki l'olam chasdo, מן המצר קראתי יה. min hametzar
karati Yah. Very last פסוק, pasuk, הודו לה' כי טוב כי לעולם
חסדו. Hodu laShem ki tov ki l'olam chasdo. So in the actual
פרק perek of תהלים, Tehillim, it starts with הודו לה' כי טוב,
Hodu laShem ki tov, it ends with הודו לה' כי טוב. Hodu
laShem ki tov. I mean for us it's such a central part
of the הלל, Hallel, who would think it's all the same פרק
perek of תהלים? Tehillim? But that's תחילה וסוף, techila v'sof, the הודו
לה' Hodu laShem at the beginning of פרק perek קי"ח kuf yud
chet and the הודו לה' Hodu laShem at the end, which is
basically the middle of הלל Hallel and the end of הלל.
Hallel. By the way, when did the church divide the תנ"ך Tanakh
into chapters?
I used to know the answer to that. But it was, yeah.
My question really is when רש"י Rashi here says פרק, perek, does
he mean what we mean by פרק? perek? Yes.
No, it was
already done by the eleventh century.
No, no, no, he doesn't mean the church פרק. perek. He means
the מסורה Masora way of dividing. Okay. Right. So anyway, okay. ובאנא
ה' הושיעה נא, uve'anna Hashem hoshi'ah na, דברי בית הלל. divrei Beit
Hillel. בית הלל Beit Hillel says you do it at אנא ה'
הושיעה נא, anna Hashem hoshi'ah na, which is what we do. ובית
שמאי אומרים אף באנא ה' הצליחה נא. u'Beit Shammai omrim af be'anna
Hashem hatzlicha na. Even by אנא ה' הצליחה נא. anna Hashem hatzlicha
na. So that doesn't fit neatly into how בית הלל Beit Hillel
בית שמאי Beit Shammai debate, okay, you know, what exactly is that
about, not so clear. אמר רבי עקיבא, amar Rabbi Akiva, now again,
I've been telling you about how much they... There are stories in
the גמרא Gemara and it's sort of especially in סוכה Sukkah about
watching things and interpreting what happened. אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar Rabbi Akiva,
צופה הייתי ברבן גמליאל ורבי יהושע. tzofeh hayiti b'Rabban Gamliel v'Rabbi Yehoshua.
I was like peering at, I was following on רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua during הלל, Hallel, שכל העם היו
מנענעים את לולביהם, she'kol ha'am hayu m'na'anim et lulaveihem, and everybody would
be shaking their לולב at who knows what
times, והם לא נענעו אלא באנא ה' הושיעה נא ואנא ה' הצליחה
נא. v'hem lo na'anu ela b'Ana Hashem Hoshiana v'Ana Hashem Hatzlicha Na.
Okay, so we'll set to see what that's about. Let's read a
line of the גמרא and then I want to see if we
have a minute to look at an important תוספות. Tosafot נענוע
מאן דכר שמיה? Ni'anua, man d'char shmei?
Whoever said that you had to shake your לולב? So התם קאי,
hatam kai, it's going back on an earlier משנה, Mishnah בלולב, b'lulav,
כל לולב שיש בו שלשה טפחים כדי לנענע בו כשר. kol lulav
she'yesh bo shlosha t'fachim k'dei l'na'anea bo kosher. It says the לולב
needs three טפחים t'fachim to shake it, or we've added an and
or an and a טפח tefach to shake it, it's כשר, kosher,
which already put out the idea that shaking is part of לולב.
וקאמר, V'ka'amar, and it says היכא מנענעים? heichah m'na'anim? So now we're
discussing where you would shake it, even though we haven't even talked
about shaking it. Now I want to just take a minute to
talk about this important תוספות Tosafot of הודו לה' כי טוב בתחילה
ובסוף Hodu l'Hashem ki tov b'tchila u'v'sof because תוספות Tosafot, raises the
question of about the חזן chazzan for us does it at like
the, you know, you know, at the part of that sort of
responsive section, right? I mean so we do it right so what
do they do for ספרדים? Sfaradim? Get tell me what ספרדים Sfaradim
do?
We just everybody says everybody says the words הודו לה' כי טוב
כי לעולם חסדו Hodu l'Hashem ki tov ki l'olam chasdo simultaneously and
does the נענוע ni'anua and there's no response.
We just do it once at הודו לה' כי טוב. Hodu l'Hashem
ki tov. Very interesting. Okay. And the אשכנזים? Ashkenazim? נו, Nu, what
do the אשכנזים Ashkenazim do?
People tell me.
The חזן chazzan does the נענוע. ni'anua.
Yeah. And then everybody repeats—like he repeats הודו לה' כי, Hodu l'Hashem
ki,
everybody the קהל kahal says הודו לה' כי טוב Hodu l'Hashem ki
tov in response each of those—and every time the קהל kahal says
הודו לה' כי טוב, Hodu l'Hashem ki tov, the קהל kahal waves
it, right?
We only do like just each one just once. Right, right.
What does the חזן chazzan do, when does the חזן chazzan do
the נענועים? ni'anuim? When for the אשכנזים? Ashkenazim? At the
beginning and
at the end. At the end
of—he does it, he does it
the last chapter, the
last—no, no, no, but in the הודו לה' Hodu l'Hashem the responsive
הודו לה'. Hodu l'Hashem. Right.
He does it during, right, the, during the, you know, the הודו
לה' כי טוב, Hodu l'Hashem ki tov, right, יאמר נא ישראל, yomar
na Yisrael, right?
No, he just does
the נענוע ni'anua on הודו—oh, Hodu
he does it on everything.
He does it on everything.
Exactly. So where does he get off doing that if the משנה
only says it on הודו לה' כי טוב? Hodu l'Hashem ki tov?
So take a look at תוספות, Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says like
this: הודו שבתחילת
הפרק והודו בסוף,
Hodu
she'b'tchilat haperek
v'Hodu b'sof, whatever תוספות Tosafos this is... and then he says like
this:
אלא בהודו מנענע פעם אחת, Ela b'Hodu m'na'anea pa'am achat, the line
starts with the words פעם אחת, pa'am achat, וכן באנא ה' הושיעה
נא כבית הלל ולא באנא ה' הצליחה נא כבית שמאי. v'chen b'Ana
Hashem Hoshiana k'Beit Hillel v'lo b'Ana Hashem Hatzlicha Na k'Beit Shammai. Okay,
so first he says like this: טעמא דבית הלל, Ta'ama d'Beit Hillel,
what's the reason of doing it by הודו Hodu and אנא ה'
הושיעה נא? Ana Hashem Hoshiana? What's it coming from? So first he
says a fascinating part, there's a פסוק, pasuk, אף על פי שאין
אנא ה' הושיעה נא תחילת הפרק ולא סוף הפרק, Af al pi
she'ein Ana Hashem Hoshiana tchilat haperek v'lo sof haperek, if it was
just הודו Hodu you'd understand you begin it with the נענועים ni'anuim
and you end it, but what's the idea of doing it by
אנא ה' הושיעה נא? Ana Hashem Hoshiana? So he says מנענעין משום
דכתיב אז ירננו עצי היער, M'na'anin mishum d'chtiv az yerannenu atzei haya'ar,
the trees of the forest will spring out in song, לפני ה'
כי בא לשפוט את הארץ, milifnei Hashem ki va lishpot et ha'aretz,
וכתיב בתריה הודו לה' כי טוב כי לעולם חסדו, v'chtiv batrei Hodu
l'Hashem ki tov ki l'olam chasdo, וכתיב נמי בתריה ואמרו
הושיענו אלוהי ישענו. v'chtiv nami batrei v'imru hoshi'enu elohei yishenu. So the
singing out of the trees of the forest is הודו לה' כי
טוב Hodu l'Hashem ki tov and אנא ה' הושיעה נא. Ana Hashem
Hoshiana. דהיינו ירננו שמנענעין את הלולב ומשבחים בהודו, D'hainu yerannenu she'm'na'anin et
halulav u'm'shabchim b'Hodu, and the trees are like bursting forth in song
and that's the symbolic of the shaking of the לולב and they're
saying הודו לה' Hodu l'Hashem ובאנא ה' הושיעה נא. u'v'Ana Hashem Hoshiana.
I don't know what the idea of בית שמאי Beit Shammai is,
but it's a beautiful explanation of בית הלל. Beit Hillel. And then
he says: ועכשיו שנהגו ששליח ציבור אומר יאמר נא ישראל והציבור עונים
הודו, V'achshav she'nahagu she'shliach tzibbur omer yomar na Yisrael v'hatzibbur onim Hodu,
so before we even get to the shaking as Dov just told
us the whole idea that there's a responsive you know sort of
acting out of the saying it and the answering of הודו, Hodu,
וכן ביאמרו נא יראי ה' v'chen b'yomru na yirei Hashem the ציבור
tzibbur and so we do a responsive הודו, Hodu, הציבור מנענעין על
כל הודו והודו שעונים. hatzibbur m'na'anin al kol Hodu v'Hodu she'onim. So
we do it for all the הודוס, Hodus, at least we're still
doing... ...for הודו, Hodu, אבל שליח ציבור לא ינענע. aval shliach tzibbur
lo yinaneia. Don't do it on his part of the יאמר נא.
yomar na. ויש מפרשים veyesh mefarshim ששליח ציבור מנענע sheshliach tzibbur minaneia
אגב ציבורא agav tzibura דעונין בכל פעם ופעם deonim bechol paam upaam
הודו Hodu מנענע נמי שליח ציבור minaneia nami shliach tzibbur ביאמרו נא
וביאמרו נא. beyomru na uveyomru na. Okay, so that's what he says.
Yes, if you're going to respond to me by doing הודו Hodu
and shake
it, I'm going to shake it while I'm doing the יאמרו נא
ישראל yomru na Yisrael and the יאמרו נא בית אהרן yomru na
beis Aharon etc. Okay. So that's תוספות Tosafos view with our current
practice. A: the idea that there's a responsiveness, a responsive recitation, which
is not by ספרדים. Sfaradim. And once we're doing it, we do
it at every הודו Hodu and he does it at the parts
that sort of, you know, that we're responding to. Okay, so that's
our current practice and it's a very interesting idea of like the
trees bursting forth in song. Tomorrow I want to discuss the end
of תוספות Tosafos. which discusses this issue about shaking the לולב not
during הלל Hallel but at the time of the ברכה bracha and
the relationship of making the ברכה bracha and taking the לולב and
shaking the לולב during הלל. Hallel. Very central idea, we'll start tomorrow
by discussing the end of תוספות. Tosafos Okay. And that's that.
Sure, divided it in half, 12:04. 12:04.
After רש״י. Rashi.
Before רש״י.
Rashi.
After רש״י. Rashi.
Right, so he sees the transition from the תוספות to the רש״י.
Rashi.